Ready, set, go, we step over the goal line
isse nou se de fumikomu gourain
Still, we don't know anything at all
bokura wa nanimo nanimo mada shiranu
We look back as we pass the line, and it's already gone
issen koete furikaeruto mou nai
Still, we don't know anything at all
bokura wa nanimo nanimo mada shiranu
Fiercely, fiercely we move on
udatte udatte udatteku
Drenched in glistening sweat
kirameku ase ga koboreru no sa
There probably were a lot of things we didn't remember
oboetenai koto mo takusan atta darou
Everyone was just a silhouette
daremo kare mo shiruetto
Let's become adults,
daiji ni shitai mono motte otona ni naru nda
holding on to things we want to cherish
And let's keep on protecting them at all times
donna toki mo hanasazu ni mamori tsudzukeyou
Then someday...
soshitara itsu no hi ni ka
We'll be able to laugh at it all
nanimo kamo o waraerusa
Like the light and nimble dancing
hirari to hirari to matteru
Of leaves taking flight
konoha ga tonde yuku
My First Friend
（カカシ）アイツは自分の夢も現実も
諦めたりしない。
He would never give up
on his dreams, or on reality.
そういうヤツだからさ。
That's the kind of guy he is.
（カカシ）そして　アイツの
そういう歩き方が→
And the way he forges ahead
draws others towards him.
仲間を引き寄せる。
つまずきそうなら助けたくなる。
He makes you want to reach out
when he's about to stumble.
そのサポートが多ければ多いほど
ゴールに近づける。
And the greater
the support behind you,
the closer you can get
to your goal.
《オビト：ナルトの道か…》
Naruto's path...
（ナルト）くらえ！　大玉螺旋手裏剣！
Take this!
Massive Rasen Shuriken!
（カカシ）信じる仲間が集まれば→
If comrades that you trust,
gather around you...
希望も形となって
見えてくるかもしれない。
Hope can take physical form
and become visible.
俺は　そう思うんだよ。
That's what I believe, Obito.
かもな。
Perhaps...
（柱間）お前から
チャクラを吸収する木龍ぞ！
That Wood Dragon will absorb
your chakra!
（柱間）これで　お前のチャクラを
吸収する忍術も意味をなさん。
Your chakra-stealing ninjutsu
has now been nullified!
つまり　もう動けず　次の忍術は
吸収できんということだ！
In other words, you can't move
nor will you be able to extract chakra
with your next ninjutsu!
《いい間だぞ　四代目の息子よ。
Good timing, son of the Fourth!
これを決めて
その隙に封印する》
Let's get him with this
and seal him away!
ナルトが投げたってことは
あそこだ！
Naruto aimed his attack over there,
so that's where Madara is!
あそこに　マダラがいるぞ！！
（サイ）ナルト！　こっち！！
Naruto, this way!
（サイ）行くよ！
サイ！　サンキュー！
Let's go!
Thanks, Sai!
グズグズするな。　今が封印のチャンスだ。
Don't waste any time!
Now's our chance to seal him!
ナルトの攻撃を　ムダにはしないぞ！
We won't let Naruto's attack
go to waste!
（みんな）おう！！
Right!
（我愛羅）命令も　言葉すらもなく→
Without any orders...
without a single word...
皆　お前に突き動かされる。
Everyone is galvanized into action...
（我愛羅）ナルト…。
Naruto...
フッ…　俺も　その一人だがな。
And I'm one of them...
守鶴。
Shukaku...
マダラを封印するのに
お前の砂の力を借りたい。
I'd like to borrow the power of
your Sand to seal Madara.
（守鶴）砂漠層大葬か？
You mean,
the Grand Sand Mausoleum?
（我愛羅）そうだ　それも特大のな。
That's right... A giant one too.
ハーッハッハッハッハ！！
（守鶴）人柱力に縛られることも
なくなったってのに→
I'm not bound to a Jinchuriki anymore.
わざわざ　お前の言うことを
今さら聞くと思うか？
What makes you think I'd listen
to you after all this time?
命令したんじゃない。
頼んでいるのだ。
I'm not ordering you.
I'm asking you.
嫌ならばいい。
他の者の力を借りるまでだ。
If you refuse, fine.
I'll just ask one of the others.
う～ん…。
うずまきナルトか…
あの化け狐野郎と→
Naruto Uzumaki, huh?
Seems you've become friends
with that Fox Demon's brat, Gaara...
ずいぶんお友達に
なったみてえだな。　我愛羅。
協力しないなら
話は後にしてくれ　俺は行く。
If you're not going to help,
let's talk later.
I'm going.
ケッ！　そういう言い方をされると
カチンとくるな。
That tone you're using ticks me off!
狐七化け狸八化けといってな→
As they say, if a fox has
seven tricks, a tanuki has eight!
バカ狐に負ける
化け狸様じゃねえぜ。
And I, the Demon Tanuki,
will not lose to a stupid fox!
俺は　お前の頼みを
聞き入れたんじゃねえ！
I'm not doing this
because you asked!
俺様の意思で動く。　案内しろ。
I'm doing this because I want to!
Lead the way.
こっちだ。
さて。
It's this way.
Now then...
待ってくれ！
ん？
Wait up.
Huh?
俺たちも協力してやる。
We'll help too.
((だから　俺は　お前も助けてぇ))
That's why I want
to help you too...
安心しろ　俺たちは
気まぐれでやるんじゃねえ！
Don't worry.
We're not doing this on a whim.
ナルトを助けたいからだ！
We want to help Naruto.
感謝する。
I'm grateful.
砂の忍の人間
オメエもナルトの知り合いか？
Sand Shinobi human,
are you a friend of Naruto too?
It's a monster!
Stay away!
((カンクロウ：建物を盾にするんだ！
Use the buildings as a shield!
でも　中には絶対　入るな。
But do not go inside!
崩されたら生き埋めじゃ！
If they collapse,
you'll be buried alive!
大丈夫か？
Are you all right?
ああ…。
Yeah...
あれが俺の弟？
That's my kid brother?
アイツは　ただの…。
H-He's just a—!
フフフフッ…　ハッ！
フフフフッ…。
こんにちは。
Hello!
こんにちは！
Hello...
わぁ！
逃げろ！
Run!
（みんな）わぁ～！
ま…　待って！
W-Wait...!
助けて！
Help!
（我愛羅）一人にしないで！
Don't leave me by myself!
一人はイヤだ…　イヤだ。
I hate it... I hate it!
（夜叉丸）人は傷つけたり
傷つけられたりして→
People hurt others and
others hurt them...
生きてゆくものなのです。
That's how they learn to survive.
でも　人は人を→
But it's not that easy for
one person to hate another...
そう簡単には
嫌いになれないものですよ。
あっ！
血は出ないけど→
It's not bleeding, but...
ここんとこが　すごく痛いんだ。
it really hurts right around here.
それは　心の傷。
That is a wound of the heart.
他人からもらう愛情でしか
癒やせない　厄介な傷。
It's a troublesome wound that
only the love from another can cure.
愛情？
Love?
愛情は　自分の身近にいる
大切な人に→
Love is a feeling
that desires to serve a precious person
who is close to oneself,
尽くしてあげたいと慈しみ
見守る心。
to love and watch over
that person...
死ね！
それか　関わるな。
Die!
Don't get involved with him.
バカ！
見るなって！
Stupid!
Don't look.
どっか行け！
Get lost!
（夜叉丸）あなたの名は我愛羅。
Your name is Gaara...
我を愛する修羅。
自分だけを愛しなさい。
A demon that loves only itself.
One that loves only itself
and fights only for itself.
そして　自分だけのために
戦いなさい。
あなたは　愛されてなど
いなかったのだから。
Because you were never loved.
うわぁ！！
うぅ…。
うおぉっ！！
アイツは　ただのバケモノじゃ！
He's just a monster!
う…。
うぅ…　ハァ　ハァ…。
なんともないのかよ…。
D-Don't you feel anything?
（テマリ）カンクロウ…。
仲間だぞ！
Kankuro...
They were our friends!
里の仲間を…　殺しておいて
なんともないのかよ！
You killed... friends from our village...
Don't you feel anything...
ここが！　心が痛まないのかよ！
right here?!
Doesn't your heart hurt?!
(黙れ　殺すぞ))
If you don't shut up, I'll kill you.
＜我愛羅：生まれながらの
殺戮兵器。　制御不能のバケモノ。
I was a killing machine
from the time I was born...
An uncontrollable monster...
母の命を糧に生まれ
里からうとまれ→
My mother died giving birth to me...
The village ignored me...
my siblings avoided me...
兄　姉からも敬遠され→
父様からは
暗殺のターゲットとされていた。
I was made a target for
assassination by my father...
俺は孤独だった。
I was alone...
孤独な兵器に
心などいらなかった。
And a solitary weapon
didn't need a heart.
そして木ノ葉崩しに
兵器として送り込まれ→
Then I was sent as a weapon
to destroy Hidden Leaf Village...
アイツと出会ったのだ＞
where I met him.
Let's go.
((行くぞ。
（サスケ）おい　そこのお前。
Hey, you there...
名は何ていう？
What's your name?
砂漠の我愛羅。
Gaara of the Sand.
（我愛羅）
俺もお前に興味がある　名は？
I'm curious about you too.
What's your name?
うちはサスケだ。
Sasuke Uchiha.
あのさ　あのさ！　俺は　俺は？
Hey! Hey! And what about me?
(興味ない))
I'm not interested.
＜　うずまきナルト
アイツとの最初の出会いは→
Naruto Uzumaki...
My first encounter
with him was uninteresting.
本当に興味のないものだった。
だが…＞
However...
((ぜってぇ　勝つ！))
I'm definitely going to win!
＜　ことあるごとに
仲間を意識した　アイツの言動が→
But with every little incident,
his words and actions
towards his friends
俺の心に　小さな苛立ちの
さざなみを立てていった＞
began to send ripples
through my heart.
Why you!
((テメエ　ゲジマユに何しようとした？
What were you trying to do
to Bushy Brows!
殺そうとした。
I was trying to kill him.
俺の邪魔をすれば　お前らも殺す。
If you get in my way,
I'll kill you too.
As if someone like you
can kill me!
お前なんかに　俺は殺せねえよ！
I keep telling you to cut it out!
（シカマル）よせって
さっきから言ってんだろ。
コイツは　バケモノ並みの強さだ。
This guy has monster-like strength.
I have a real monster inside me.
俺は　本物のバケモン飼ってんだ。
I wouldn't lose to a guy like him!
(こんなヤツに負けねえ))
＜更に　アイツは
俺にも関わってきた。
Furthermore, he started to
have an effect on me...
それは　俺にとって→
He wasn't like the others
who merely aroused hatred in me.
憎悪をかきたてる以外の
何者でもなかった＞
((我愛羅：コイツらは
お前にとって何だ？
Just what are they to you?
俺の仲間だってばよ！
He's my friend!
これ以上
ちっとでも傷つけてみやがれ。
If you even attempt to hurt him,
I'll pummel you!
テメエぶっ飛ばすぞ！
A friend?!
仲間？　笑わせる！
Don't make me laugh...
俺は　自分のためだけに…。
I only fight...
戦う！
for myself!
自分に似てるから
おんなじような寂しさとか→
Because he resembles me...
Because he has gone through life
with the same loneliness
and sadness as I have...
悲しさとか
感じて生きてきたから→
そんな孤独のなかで→
That guy who continued to fight
in solitude for himself,
自分のためだけに
戦うお前を強いと思った。
I thought he was strong.
But that's not the meaning
of true strength...
でも　本当に強いって
そんなことじゃなかったはずだ。
自分だけのために戦ったって
本当は　強くなれねえんだ。
If one fights just for oneself
in solitude,
one can't become truly strong...
ハァーッ！
多重影分身の術。
Multi-Shadow Clone Jutsu!
(う　ず　ま　き　ナルト二千連弾の巻))
Na-Ru-To! 2K Uzumaki...
Barrage!
《我愛羅：この俺が　こんな…
こんなヤツに負けるはずあるか！》
There's no way...
I can lose...
to a guy like him!
＜アイツは　追い詰めれば
追い詰めるほど→
The more I drove him into a corner,
the harder he fought back...
より強い力を発揮し始めた＞
Summoning Jutsu!
((口寄せの術！
変化の術！
Transformation Jutsu!
(起きやがれ　この野郎！))
Get up, you jerk!
＜何度も何度も　どん底から…＞
Time and time again...
after hitting rock bottom...
Die!
((死ね！
こんちくしょうが！
You bastard!
Why...?
《なぜ　コイツは　これほど強い…》
What kind of strength
does he possess?
Why?
なんで…　なんでお前は
他人のために　そこまで…。
Why do you go so far for others?
Because they are my precious friends
who saved me from that hell,
一人ぼっちの
あの地獄から救ってくれた…。
of being alone, and who acknowledged
my existence.
俺の存在を認めてくれた…。
大切な　みんなだから…。
Love...
愛情…。
Is that why he is so strong?
(だから　コイツは強いのか…))
＜　この日は　俺にとって
特別な日となった。
This day would come to
hold special meaning for me...
I learned that he grew up
under the same circumstances as me,
自分と同じ境遇を持ちながらも→
yet he chose
a different way to live...
自分とは違う生き方があったこと。
And that my strength was
directly connected to this.
そして　それが己の強さに→
つながっていることを
知ったのだ＞
((我愛羅：努力し
自ら切りひらくしかないんだ。
I just have to work hard and
carve out a future for myself.
一人きりの孤独な道に逃げずに…。
And I must not run away
from my path of solitude.
If I do that, someday...
そうすれば　いつかアイツのように…。
I can be like him.
So as a shinobi
who belongs to the Sand,
だから俺は　砂の一人の忍として
風影を目指す。
I will aim to become the Kazekage.
この里につながり生きるために…。
In order to connect with
this village and live in it.
Gaara...
我愛羅…。
うずまきナルトを見て　そう思った。
Watching Naruto Uzumaki
makes me feel this way.
他者とのつながり。
俺にとって　それは→
A connection with others...
Until now, that only meant hatred
and a desire to kill.
今まで憎しみと
殺意でしかなかった。
So just what is this connection
that he keeps talking about?
しかし　アイツが
あそこまでして言う→
つながりとは
いったい何なのか…。
After all this time, I understand
a little bit about something...
今頃になって俺にも少しだけ
わかったことがある。
Suffering and sadness...
even happiness...
苦しみや悲しみ　喜びも→
他の誰かと分かち合うことが
できるのだと…。
can be shared with someone.
うずまきナルト…　アイツは
俺と同じ苦しみを知っていた。
Naruto Uzumaki...
He has known
the same suffering I have...
And he has taught me
そして　生きる道を変えることが
できることを教えてくれた。
that it is possible to
change one's path in life...
I, too, want to become the kind of man
that everyone looks up to...
俺も　いつか　誰かに必要とされる
存在になりたい。
Instead of just being
a weapon to be fearful of.
(恐るべき兵器としてではなく
砂隠れの風影として))
As the Kazekage of the Hidden Sand.
I was able to take a step forward,
away from my pessimistic life.
＜後ろ向きだった俺の人生は→
ようやく一歩前に踏み出せたのだ。
そして　俺は風影となった。
And I became the Kazekage.
I have gained more friends,
多くの仲間を得て→
and I continue to strive to be
someone who is needed by others.
これからもっと他者から
必要とされる存在となり→
And with my head held high,
I stood as his equal,
そして　胸を張って　アイツと対等に→
and step by step,
友と認められる日を目指して
前へ前へと歩み始めたのだ。
I aimed for the day when
I could be acknowledged as his friend.
しかし…＞
However...
《誰だ…　この手。
Whose... hand is this?
なんだ　俺の手か》
Oh... it's my hand.
《俺は　誰かに必要とされる
存在になれたのだろうか。
Have I become someone
who is needed by somebody?
Huh?
あれ？　なんだ…　俺？》
What is this?
It's me?
《あれが俺…　誰かに
必要とされたがってた俺。
That's me...
I really wanted to be needed...
Why? Why did I desire that?
どうして　なんで
そうなりたかったんだろう。
Why am I someone
who desires that?
俺は　なんで　それを
望む存在なんだろう？
あの目　あの鼻　あの口。
Those eyes...
that nose, that mouth...
Why?
なぜ…　なぜ　あれが我愛羅。
Why is that Gaara?
俺は　その中にいた。
I was inside that...
No... Actually just what am I?
いや　そもそも俺とは何だ？
俺と自覚してるだけで→
That's what I feel I am...
But actually... what am I?
そもそも　何者なんだ？
Just a small feeling?
ただの小さな感覚》
我愛羅　我愛羅！
Gaara... Gaara!
Who is that?
《誰だ　誰を呼んでる？》
Who are you calling?
《誰だ？　この手。
Who is it?
Who's hand is this?
なんだ　また俺の手か。
Oh... It's just my hand again...
俺の手…。
My hand...
俺？
Me?
俺とは誰だ？
Who am I?
I...
俺…》
《俺は…》
I am...
When the Akatsuki extracted
the Tailed Beast from me...
＜暁に捕らえられ
尾獣を抜かれた俺が…。
I died, but was revived...
一度は死んだ俺が
生き返ることができたのは→
thanks to Granny Chiyo
チヨバア様の
命を引きかえにした禁術と→
who used a Forbidden Jutsu
to exchange her life for mine,
and Naruto's chakra.
ナルトのチャクラのおかげだったという＞
((カンクロウ：じゃあな。
お　おう…。
So long.
Right!
普通なら　ここで握手とかして
別れんだろうけど→
Normally, people shake hands
when they part.
But I'm not so good with
stuff like that...
俺ってば　そういうの
苦手だからな。
So...
(このまま…))
＜俺は
お前に友と認められたくて→
I thought I've been doing my best
in order to be accepted
by you as a friend.
努力してきたつもりだった。
I thought I had to become someone
who was essential to others...
もっと他者に必要とされ→
someone people looked up to...
認められる存在にならねばと
励んできた。
But...
だが…＞
＜俺たちは　あの日
互いを理解し→
But on that day, we...
came to understand,
and accept each other...
存在を認め合う仲…
友になっていたのだな＞
We were already friends.
どうした？
What's wrong?
I asked if you are Naruto's friend?
オメエもナルトの知り合いかと
聞いたんだ。
Yeah...
あぁ　最初の友だ。
He's my first friend.
そうか。
Is that right?
All right, let's hurry.
（我愛羅）よし　急ごう。
kimi ni makechai sou na kurai
Almost to the point of losing to you
kimi ni nayamasare sou da
Feeling like you might torment me
kimi ni kikoecha dame dame dame da
Not wanting you to hear me no, no, no
kimi ni nagasare sou na kurai
Swept away by you
kimi ni shiteyarare sou da
Taken in by you
kimi o omoccha dame dame dame da
I shouldn't love you no, no, no
sugu wasurechatte dame da
It's not good that I'm so forgetful
uzukumattecha dame da
It's not good that I'm cowering
kizutsuitatte ana aitatte
Even if I'm wounded and pierced
massugu tatteirareruyou ni naritai
I want to be able to stand up straight
kimi ni makechai sou na kurai
Almost to the point of losing to you
kimi ni nayamasare sou da
Feeling like you might torment me
kimi ni kikoecha dame dame dame da
Not wanting you to hear me no, no, no
kimi ni nagasare sou na kurai
Swept away by you
kimi ni shiteyarare sou da
Taken in by you
kimi o omoccha dame dame dame da
I shouldn't love you no, no, no
I'm curious about what happens
next with Gaara...
＜旬の小鉢が大好きな豆助＞
But the next episode is
a little extra feature.
In the Hyuga Clan, Hinata and
Hanabi were very close sisters!
But the destiny of hatred
within the Hyuga
豆助　きょうは今が旬の
あれを使った小鉢よ
caused their feelings
to pass each other by.
Next time on Naruto Shippuden:
"The Adored Elder Sister."
＜　その小鉢とは？＞
Can't destiny be changed?
＜　それは…→
１年の中でも　とりわけ…＞